[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
is your mobile app really secure new
vulnerabilities pop up
every day securing your app's valuable
ip and data is critical
guard square's security solutions are
built for developers and protect your
app at every stage in the development
life cycle
multiple layers of protection
automatically detect tampering and make
your app a difficult target for
attackers
learn more at guardsquare.com se radio
[Music]
hello everyone this is felina for
software engineering radio
today with me on the show are two guests
the first
guest is kevlin henny he is an
independent consultant
trainer coder and writer and he's given
keynotes tutorials and workshops at
hundreds of conferences
around the world he's the co-author of a
pattern language for distributed
computing
and on patterns and pattern languages
the second
guest today is trisha gee she has
developed java applications for a range
of industries in finance manufacturing
software for companies of all sizes
trisha is currently a developer advocate
at jetbrains
a leader of the sevilla java user group
and a java
champion together kathleen and trisha
edited the book
97 things every java programmer should
know
welcome to the show so i just read your
book and it's really
packed with super interesting facts and
information
even though i am not a java programmer
and have never been a java programmer i
really learned a lot
and many of the tips are also very
generic in nature
so my plan today for the show is that i
just asked you about a few of the
97 things that everyone should know and
afterwards we will also ask you about
your favorite things to know
so one of the chapters that i
specifically liked is chapter five about
encapsulation
and the author of this chapter etchan
yanaga argues that encapsulation is
actually one of the oo principles
that is used least so that's actually
the first thing that i want to dive into
a bit
what is encapsulation because if it's
not used so often people might also not
be so aware of what
encapsulation is the way i'd put it is
and the way edson kind of explores it um
because the specific title of his piece
is behavior is easy state is hard
and it's this idea of this kind of
relationship
that we want to get out that when many
people
think about encapsulation they just
think about a kind of a light
veneer just make a few things private
yeah make the fields private that's it
it just kind of washes over it we
i've kind of i've kind of scrubbed a
little bit of private on on the data
and we're all good whereas actually
what's really going on for encapsulation
is this idea of how do i use it what's
the interface how do i want to use it
and if there's something much richer
that's going on there so often as
developers we
tend to think from the inside out you
know you're presented on screen
here in my fields i can see everything i
have a privileged view
whereas from the outside you don't get
that and so we tend to think oh
my fields i'm going to add some getters
and setters rather than thinking
what's this object for how do you use it
what is the intention behind it and
these are far
far harder questions and that is what
guides the
state of changeable objects um for
example
rather than thinking like you know
nudging flags here and collections there
so often you look at some java you look
at java code
and in some systems you get a feeling
yep there's collections and there's
strings and there's integers and there's
flags
you don't really get a sense of things
in a capsule quite literally encapsulate
to put something in a capsule means
there's a boundary and we want to care
about how do we
look at that boundary the interface and
what are we hiding away from people it's
not just my choice of data
representation it's
the mechanics if you like so that's
really what he's getting at and you can
see that's
a lot deeper than i guess many people
think of when we think of
encapsulation as oh it's just private
fields that's it
it's a bigger story and therefore it's
more complex
i think something else was interesting
from that piece was so he mentions the
beginning he mentions polymorphism and
inheritance
and i think one of the anti-patterns
that's quite common especially
when you're learning to program java is
is kind of the opposite of encapsulation
using inheritance to just kind of like
grab everything and expose everything so
my object is one of everything it's like
the opposite of encapsulated
so i think his point was very
interesting about how and i've been in
interviews where i've been asked about
polymorphism and inheritance
and not been asked about encapsulation
about
things like you know do one thing and do
it properly and only expose the things
which are important to
to the person using this object so yeah
it was an interesting piece there
so can you give a concrete example of a
use case or a business case where
the situation that kathleen just
described occurred why you had code that
indeed just
painted a little bit of encapsulation on
top of code
and that you may be changed or
refactored into
using encapsulation as edson janaga
argues here i'm not sure i could think
of a specific one i can think of this
happening a bunch of times
where especially again especially using
inheritance where
you think you have let's say a
i don't know like a book order object
but
with because it's using inheritance it
also has like
a bunch of other order type
characteristics
and you see this sometimes it's bled
over from a relational database where
your relational database has like flags
for it's not one of these is one of
these
isn't one of those does have one of
those and sometimes you get it because
you have this enormous inheritance
hierarchy whereby
you yeah you're basically like i think
the example in design patterns was about
hierarchies for ducks and so when you
have like a rubber duck
that doesn't fly and it doesn't quack it
squeaks but it probably has a
does fly or it does quack type method on
it so you can you the user have to
figure out like
what is this object which is the
opposite of object-oriented programming
whereby you should just get a rubber
duck and not care about
all of the other types of ducts which
may or may not be blowing into its type
yeah i think that that's one of those
areas where you can kind of
again specific examples in in most cases
it's not just
uniquely because um something was
unencapsulated normally there's a bunch
of other things going on
and it starts with the question when
somebody says is 100 fields too many for
a class
and at that point you know that just
from the question you already know
something is amiss
and in other words that you've ended up
with something that has just aggregated
data and astritis says you know
sometimes it's just like yep i've taken
the database you know it's just like
straight
straight in i've just taken the schema
and rather than saying you know what
some of these are behavioral a flag is
normally an indication of
a behavior it's a kind of thing but
there's no subtyping in the database so
we don't end up with that rich model in
the code we end up with a very flat
model it's just basically sort of data
transfer objects with a couple of other
methods and
there's a lot of data there's these
buckets of data and then that kind of
style permeates through the rest of the
code and then somebody comes to maintain
it they add a thing they add a thing
maybe somebody else has got the kind of
like yup i've got the inheritance hammer
it's my turn to hit everything with it
or i've seen this the idea of like well
i've reduced the number of fields here
by pushing them up into superclasses and
it's like actually that might make the
problem worse because
they're all still there but i can't see
them directly
and now i've got protected data which is
so in other words it's normally
symptomatic of something else it's very
rarely just the one
thing so i think that's the thing is
normally what you do is you find one
spot you kind of pull and you go oh okay
this is connected to this is connected
to this
yeah so i said that many of the
things that people should know are not
so java specific but this chapter
actually has some java specific advice
related to encapsulation because the the
chapter says
that you should not auto generate
setters
so why is this good advice why does this
help the code to be more encapsulated
behavior at the easy state is hard
because once you start having setters
once you start having mutability
then you can't make any reasoning about
what the behavior should be because
sometimes the behavior is based on if
i've got one of these or i don't have
one of these or this isn't null or that
is null
you're mutating kind of the when you're
mutating the state of an object
it becomes very difficult to reason
about what you've got and how it should
behave
and in fact some of this is kind of java
is is changing to become
more immutable first it's not really as
far as
immutable but like final first or
no setters first like records for
example are
which is a new feature in java 16 will
you can create a new record instance
with new fields
but um you can't set those this is like
basically an immutable object where you
don't change things because
but having mutability there to begin
with by default was one of those things
which led to some of these
anti-patterns that were talking about
some of these bugs which is difficult to
debug like i don't know
now this object has been through these
various workflows i don't know what it
is or how it should behave
yeah and i think that is really that is
that issue is that
culturally we have this kind of much
more imperative mindset that
immutability is a thing you ask for
mutability is a thing you get for free
and we kind of moved into a very
different time here where
people started thinking you know what
there's a lot of reasons that's not true
but that challenge the setters the auto
setters even if you have something auto
generating setters and that's the
problem is we've ended up with saying
well
i always have setters or i often have
setters it's become such a ritual
that people auto generate it through
their fingers if nothing else is going
on they'll do it through their fingers
you don't need a tool to do that
they don't even know that they're doing
it so often what you'll end up with is
that kind of
a kind of addition that kind of like yep
i'm putting this here
and perhaps if you were writing this in
a if you were focused on the tests you
would see that and go wait a minute why
am i doing this i never actually
i've got a setup but i've never tested
for it and it's that simple idea that
asking a question is easy but changing
the world is a lot harder
the way that you can change an object is
often subtle and you can put things into
invalid states
and therefore you end up propagating
code elsewhere that should probably be
either not there at all or should be
contained encapsulated
within the object the encaps the
encapsulation boundary is
i'm looking after the state i'm going to
make sure either it doesn't change or it
changes in very well defined ways
and i shouldn't have other people in the
workflow going hey
can i just check in on you at this point
um what state are you in you know
the nightmare scenario is a piece of
code i saw a few years ago
that it suffered all these things as i
say there's normally it's a system
of issues it's never one issue it's
normally a system of things
big classes long methods lots of hands
in the code lots of very quick changes
so there's no kind of sense of
architectural consistency or style
everything was kind of in panic mode but
that also led to the feeling when you're
reading through the code
that if you ask me what does this code
do i would probably say i wouldn't say
oh
it quotes for mortgages which is what
the system was supposed to do i'd say
mostly this code checks for null and it
logs
because it was forever wait a minute i
wonder if this is is this still null
it wasn't a thousand lines ago but maybe
that's changed in the last thousand
lines there was a complete sense of
we'd lost the model as it were there was
no sense of reasoning
as tricia pointed out this kind of idea
that you should be able to reason about
your code so
you kind of lose that and then it
becomes it just becomes well i guess in
these times we can say viral
it just spreads you know and and that
becomes a symptom in the code and that's
the idea again encapsulation it's a
boundary it's
it's it's trying to keep things
contained and if your rule is nothing
changes then that's where the
containment comes
if you're all things is things only
change in specific well-defined ways in
the way that other
objects can use it rather than how do i
change an into how do i change a boolean
that becomes that's quite different in
that sense people are often tackling
it at the kind of like the flag level
rather than what makes sense for this
object and those setters
often don't have the right validation so
you can quite happily put an object into
an inconsistent state
which kind of that shouldn't be that's
that's kind of not an object really so i
think to summarize the advice is that
you shouldn't owe to generate setters
because setters is something you should
really consider you should really
think what is it that i want here what
should
and shouldn't happen with this object if
you just generate them as you said as a
ritual you just make them either
automatically or you just write them
by habits then you aren't thinking about
you aren't modeling or you're just
adding some plumbing state change is a
privilege
not a right nice that's a great quote
so i want to move on to chapter six
chapter six is about breaking up
problems into
chunks so firstly i would like to hear
like what is your summary of this
because
clearly breaking up a problem into
separate pieces like that's a good thing
but what is the core of this chapter i
really like this chapter from jean
because
it was it's a common thing that you hear
like
when you're doing small pieces of toy
engineering obviously you've got small
pieces of work that you can do you can
break stuff into chunks when you do real
engineering it becomes much more
difficult to break i use a story down
into discrete tasks
i think there's sometimes confusion
between breaking down something into
small pieces of business value which can
be difficult to do
and breaking something into small tasks
which can be
implemented and checked in without
breaking the code or without making any
major changes
and so this is something that she's
she's kind of talking about in this
piece that
we as developers can often end up
working on a piece of code for like
two weeks on a business piece of value
for about two weeks
and at the end of it maybe we've changed
i don't know maybe only three files
maybe 100 files but like
we still haven't been able to make the
smallest possible commit
to source control or we still haven't
been able to hand over to someone else
and that's because in our minds we're
like well this is a special
piece of work it's got all these
dependencies and it's not ready
until i've done everything but in this
piece she takes a couple of examples and
shows how
you can be like look you can break it
down into
you know i'm just going to write i'm
going to output something to the command
line i'm going to read something from a
file i'm going to iterate over it i'm
going to make this filter i'm going to
do this change
just because it doesn't change the
functionality in the application as a
whole
doesn't mean it's not a small
committable piece
of work so you can still commit the
piece of code which
reads from a file even if you don't do
anything with that file yet
you can still commit um i'm a big big
big fan of committing like skeleton code
like sketching out code like
perhaps you've got unit tests for maybe
even larger sort of functional level
tests but they're not hooked into your
main application yet so you can kind of
sketch out pieces of functionality the
user is never going to
see yet because you haven't plumbed them
in but you can break that down to
smaller tasks and commit them
it's definitely is a skill it's a
difficult thing to do
to break your work down into small tasks
but just because it's difficult doesn't
mean
it can't or shouldn't be done then
how do i know what is a committable
piece of work so so i i'm programming
and i'm indeed i'm adding a bit here and
there and oh i'm adding a new feature so
this class needs to change
how do i stop myself from committing
this whole blob of change
when i worked at at lmax which i i
worked out in london a couple uh like 10
years ago now a couple years ago 10
years ago
and i work with people like dave farley
who wrote the continuous delivery book
and martin thompson who's now fairly
famous for talking about mechanical
sympathy and i work with all these great
people
who were very well steeped in extreme
programming and agile
stuff they kind of taught me some of
this stuff like one of the ways that you
know that it's ready to commit is you
can have a unit test
so you've only added a couple of lines
of code like i said it's not plumbed
into perhaps the user interface
but i've written a method which exposes
some functionality and i have a unit
test
it compiles the test passes the build
passes
i can commit that and you can do that
with just like two lines of code or in
java probably like six because methods
are quite long
but you know you just do it on a on a
small few lines of code basis and
the thing is that if you have unit tests
and we also had end-to-end acceptance
tests
if you have unit tests and they pass and
the end-to-end acceptance test pass
then you can commit it's safe to commit
you know you can do that
i think that idea of the couple points
to trisha mention which are
really key in terms of that workflow the
first is
that idea of can we break this down it
is a skill
you can break this one down uh by
learning to do it often when we approach
things we have one big idea in our head
and it's
it becomes an act of almost performance
i must do it all at once it's all in my
head
and it must now i'm now going to be
glued to my keyboard and it's going to
flow from my head through my fingertips
with the assistance of pizza and coffee
and all the rest of it's a performance
act
rather than thinking okay what's the
next bit what's the next small bit
what's the bit that moves it towards
that and the way that i work with
clients in this i always say well
what's half of what you're thinking you
know you're thinking something
what's half of what you're thinking that
is still reasonable
okay and what's half of that and then
that other point about
the really simple point of does it work
not does
everything work as i am planning for it
to work at some point in the future but
at this point is it a meaningful step
and honestly
the bottom line is so trish is talking
about
all the really good stuff let's just
start with the really simple stuff does
it compile
okay honestly i have seen i i've seen
things in
version control systems you people
wouldn't believe and they wouldn't
compile
so yeah the bottom line is does it
actually compile you know that really
has to be the simplest thing
and then moving up through various
versions of it works you know the very
simple idea of i've added something
and is it meaningful is what could i
describe what i've just done well yes
i've just added a method here or i've
added a special case we're not
exploiting it elsewhere but here's a
here's a piece of
code in the test that demonstrates the
existence of that special case handling
and that's fine that's a stepping stone
which i think is the other thing is
there's an older term for it
i picked this one up off grady booch
years ago in one of his books about 30
years ago
stable intermediate forms of just for
the just for the listeners by the way
i'm only in my 30s of course i was just
very precocious
as a child but i was reading this stuff
and there's this lovely phrase stable
intermediate forms that he got from
herbert simon economist and you know
general
polymath and this idea of stable
intermediate forms that
although you've got a big goal in mind
rather than having some big bang moment
where everything comes together
miraculously or not
what are the intermediate forms that
also work it's like walking versus
running
when you walk um you always have at
least one point of contact with the
ground therefore you are stable you can
pause and it's safe
if you run the definition of running is
that you go zero one
zero one and there's something very
binary about that and developers do love
that they love the running i must do it
all at once
but if you trip the whole thing falls
apart if you're distracted the whole
thing falls apart if it is not all
complete then you don't have a thing
whereas with walking it's like okay i
can pause now yep i can check that in i
can do whatever
it's on route and it's stable it's good
as it is
rather than oh please don't use that
it's all kind of hanging
it's all hanging by pieces of string and
good hope
so that is that idea that and and i
think
jean's piece is really good in kind of
highlighting this
and just starting you know it's also
quite good in terms of her storytelling
which i think is
it really brings the piece to life
moving on to the next chapter one
chapter that also
caught my attention is chapter 21
because that chapter is about thinking
in sql or thinking like you would in sql
so it's a bit surprised i was like well
this book is about java but now you're
you're saying actually think like i
should use sql
thinking so what is that what is sql
thinking
it's logical isn't it so that's dean
wampler's piece
and what i like about this is the a lot
of what he's talking about
yeah he's leading with with sql but what
he's really in one sense talking about
is declarative thinking
if you want to open it up it's just it's
just that sequel is our natural hook
it's the it is the logic programming
language that
um most people know that they don't know
that they know as a logic programming
language
so it's just that opening idea of like
you know how would i ask a question
i've got a whole load of data how would
i ask a question well you know what
let's set up a for loop no that's not
how we ask the question is
you start framing it i want to select
things tell me the criteria that matter
okay so it's kind of flipping away the
uh it's i mean we might say one level
it's inverting the control flow but
actually what we're trying to do is
discard the control flow and say you
know what
you've written loops all your life you
have written all the loops
as a developer you have written all the
loops you will ever need to write you've
written the loop where you do something
for everything in a collection you've
written the loop where you search for
something
there's only a handful of loops and you
have written them all
many times and there's this idea of like
well what's your intention
and it's that idea that he's trying to
get us drawn into it's like
what is the intention of this piece i am
trying to select these from where well
okay under what conditions what's the
thing that matters
in this and really to look at our
collections
and our data sets from that point of
view which naturally leads you into kind
of yeah
it's a broader clarity space but it
naturally leads you into thinking in
terms of streams
it naturally leads you into having a
slightly more
a better relationship with your
collections i guess rather than poking
and prodding them with for loops and ifs
it's kind of like what's our goal here
let's figure out the flow
but not the control flow somebody else
has already done that and that kind of
thinking
is quite powerful so that's the thing is
you say you know hey what's this sequel
thinking in
in the middle of a job it's like what
he's trying to do is make you recognize
you already know this stuff but perhaps
haven't had the opportunity to bring it
home
you know you do it in one language
bringing it to java
because as a pharmacy sharp developer i
of course
think about link about actual language
features
that enable this sql-like thinking is
there something like this in java are
there language features or concepts that
support this
form of thinking yeah so and it's fairly
recent in java's history
so java 8 got the streams api which
kevlin referred to so finally we could
instead of
iterating over and pulling stuff out of
our collections we could say
for every one of well actually the worst
one is for everyone do this thing
but better would be like filter this
collection for something which looks
like this
order by this you know and so streams
came in java 8.
and that's one of the things that really
helped me get my head around streams
when that came in
was thinking about sql the fact that you
would be like you know
instead of you don't tell the database
how to get its data
you tell it what you want and and kind
of turning the thinking on its head was
what was required to understand how
streams worked
yeah and there is a difference in the
sense from c
sharp because the link stuff if you like
it's the way that streams are
represented so the two things happen in
java 8
one was the streams and the other was
lambdas that gives you that richness
and those were in c sharp sooner but
link
added an additional layer of sugaring
over the top if you like what you get in
java there's no
extra language support but what it's the
link unlinked in other words
if you delink it you start looking at
what's there the dot where
and all the rest of it that's what
you're getting in java is as if you're
writing the raw version
rather than the syntax triggered version
that's the distinction there
the next chapter that i want to talk
about is chapter 43
about type inference so as i said i'm
not much of a java expert so i actually
learned from this chapter that since
java 11
there is local variable type inference
in java
what is that what is local variable type
inference
it's just a long way of saying that you
can type var
instead of your type name on the left
hand side
so there's always been a lot of
criticism about java being full of
boilerplate and one of the things is for
example
like in the in the very old days you
just have to say
list string my list equals
new arraylist string and everyone's
going why do i need to say all of those
things so many times
java 7 introduced the diamond operator
so you didn't need to say the string
inside the chevrons inside the generics
on two sides and java technically java
10 which so it's in java 11
introduced local variable type inference
so that you can now just say
var my list equals new arraylist string
and so and it does what it says on the
tin it's type inference it's not
one of the misleading things is some
people think it's a bit like groovy's
def
where you kind of have a kind of fluffy
type with dynamic typing
but um but it's not it's like if i can
tell from the right hand side what the
type should be i will use the right hand
type instead of you having to
literally type it two times on each side
but it's local variables so it's inside
methods only you can't use it for fields
you can't use it for parameters you can
only use it for methods for variables
inside your methods
and i think that's quite nice from that
point of view that
it's a kind of agreement between it's
kind of like a three-way agreement it's
it's you the code base and the compiler
it's like you're looking at it you get i
know what the type is the compiler is
going yeah i know what the type is and
it's just like well why do we have to
tell the source code the type because
you and me have already agreed on this i
can tell look at the thing on the right
hand side you know we all know what it
is why do we have to spell it out again
so there's that but it's got a little
bit of restraint and
that's the point that trish said it's
just like you know what if i put this
everywhere
if it's local then i can see everything
that i need to the minute i start
hitting the field
level it becomes a little more brittle
both from the reader's point of view but
also some of the changes that you could
accidentally make
in a field initializer that suddenly
changed actually changed the
representation of your class which is
probably not what you planned
so there's reasons to put a little bit
of restraint and say you know what in
the privacy of your own method
we're all good we can see stuff we can
everybody knows and there's very few
surprises or opportunities for surprises
it's kind of like a
an agreement with that and so it does
ease the i mean sometimes when people
describe
the language as strongly typed it's just
like yeah and i'm typing and i'm typing
and i'm typing you know there's a lot of
letters there that's why we have auto
completion
because there's a remarkable amount of
typing otherwise
and really that's still heavy on the eye
so it just eases that and we see this in
a number of other languages you
mentioned c sharp before that
that had that we find that in functional
languages with hindley milner type
systems
c plus plus got an equivalent thing
everybody's kind of going i think we've
gone through the idea that we all know
what we're talking about let's let the
source code acknowledge that too so it
picks up on a valuable trend there
so i think what you're saying is that it
doesn't only save you
time in typing and actually typing the
characters but it also makes your code
more readable because you don't have
this double irrelevant information that
you still have to process
yeah you have to do a lot of one of the
things that if you like that has
happened
since there's a few features that allow
the code to find its way a little bit
further left
towards the reading line you know it
says there's a lot of java code that
kind of wanders off the right hand side
of the screen it's just like oh come on
hold yourself back in you know we're
still human we still have a limited
ability to read really long things and
it just shorts lines
makes things accessible and readable the
most interesting thing is normally
the variable name what role is i'm going
to see this variable name again many
times so
it's introducing yourself hi i'm this
variable guess what this is what i'm
initialized to
and you know i take my time from that
rather than here's a whole load of
ceremony like giving somebody a whole
load of honorific titles up front and we
still
don't know what they're called it's just
like i am senior principal
yes but what's your name what do i call
you it's now okay
you know hi i'm fred and here's all the
other stuff should you care
it's not hidden away it's all there it's
just that we avoid having to repeat it
and we put it in the right place
yeah that totally makes sense
elastic enables the world's leading
organizations to put their data to work
using the power of search
whether it's connecting people and teams
with content that matters
keeping applications and infrastructure
online or protecting entire digital
ecosystems
elastic's search platform is able to
surface relevant results with speed and
at scale
learn how you can get started with
elastic's search platform for free at
elastic.co
e radio
moving on to chapter 54 this is your
your own chat or tricia because many of
the chapters are written by your
co-authors but this is
your own personal chapter in which you
argue that your ide and then
specifically jetbrains can do a lot for
you so i'm really curious
what are some of your favorite tips what
are things
the ide can do for me that i don't know
yet
so i have so many tips for using the ide
that most of my conference presentations
are about how to use the ide
we had a whole intellij idea conference
last year last week which was
two seven hour days of content on how to
use the ide
which should be available on youtube if
anyone's interested but like
i'll try and restrict us to a small
number of features
we were talking earlier about things
like type inference
where it makes the code easier to read
sometimes but sometimes
losing that typed out type information
makes it more difficult to read the ide
can help you read your code with things
like type hints
both for local variable type inference
and also for things like parameter names
parameters
that you pass into methods so for
reading code navigating code the ide is
really really helpful
generating code we talked a bit about
why not to generate code why not to
generate setters
but in java there are times when you are
going to want to generate
getters setters hash code equals
constructors
and tostring and there is really no need
to write that stuff
out the ide will do it for you so by all
means just use the
code generation features another part of
code generation i really like inside the
ide
and again it comes back to the fact that
i like writing unit tests
i like to write my unit test first i
like to code i like to write the test
to code against the api the way i would
like it to be
so instead of using your classic ide
features which is
code suggestions and and code completion
do the opposite
type out all the code the way that you
expect it to be and if the ide says this
method doesn't exist in the shape that
you made it
then it will create that code for you so
that allows you to think outside in it
allows you to define the api the way it
makes sense from the calling point of
view
instead of writing the internals of the
class and then trying to expose it
in a sensible way so i like that kind of
outside in
code generation favorite features as
well see i told you i could go on about
this for ages
refactoring particularly inside intellij
idea but
all of these features are available
inside your favorite ide it doesn't have
to be intellij idea
but the refactoring tools renaming you
should not be doing a search and replace
you should be using the refactoring
tools to rename your methods your
variables your classes
in all the places they need renaming and
no the ide will do it correctly so
everything still compiles
these automatic refactoring tools mean
that everything compiles you don't have
to recompile and fix things up
afterwards
and that's what you can rely on your ide
to do your ide uses the compiler it uses
its own internal logic to figure out
like what is the right way to do this
how do i keep the code green and make
everything still
semantically the same as it was before
so refactoring is like
one of my favorite things and then just
one last thing
in intellij ideas specifically the
inspections so inspections cover a whole
broad range of things like oh have you
thought about doing this for loop
as an enhanced for loop instead of an
indexed for loop
it does things like now you're using
java 8 or beyond you could use the
streams api
and in particular i like the fact that
the inspections in intellij idea will
help you
migrate to modern versions of java so it
will tell you things like you can use
the streams api
java 8 isn't so modern anymore but
streams api you can use
local variable type inference so you can
use var if you want to
new features which will be coming in
java 16 include records
we already have records and pattern
matching for instance of
and we now have things like text blocks
and
switch expressions these are all things
which kind of help get rid of some
old-fashioned looking java code and turn
it into something more readable more
succinct
and just generally prettier and the ide
will just say
did you know you can use the new
features in java so you don't need to go
and find that stuff
out so that ide will do that for you so
that is a not so quick summary of some
of my favorite features inside the ide
so then kathleen it's only fair and you
also get to talk about your chapter of
course so your chapter is 85 and your
chapter is about
checked exceptions which is a really
java specific thing
so firstly for the people in the
audience that aren't java programmers
what are checked exceptions right
checked exceptions
are exceptions that uh the compiler
will check um as opposed to the run time
in other words
there's a basically anything that
derives from
anything that subclasses from exception
or actually throwable but it's not also
a runtime exception
and there's not an error in other words
these are kind of like platform level
errors
and runtime exceptions are kind of like
the ordinary small change exceptions
that you might expect oops i
index past the end of an array type
exception oh dear i seem to have
dereferenced a null
type of exception in other words small
change ones the ones that are like to
happen everywhere because they're going
to be really noisy
they get an exemption from this there
was this idea with checked exceptions
of why don't we make the exception modes
of a method
why don't we make that part of the type
signature and this is one of those kind
of ideas that sounds initially
quite good it's it's quite well
intentioned in other words the
regular signature of the method gives
you the happy day behavior
i pass these arguments and i get this
result back we're all good
but what happens when it goes wrong well
let's acknowledge exceptions as first
class in that sense and
and have a throws clause that shows you
the exceptions that are thrown
this is great in theory first language
that i know of
was uh that did this was barbara
liskoff's uh clue language
so 1970s that language hugely influenced
languages after
it with exceptions but there's this idea
of you ha
making it part of the type system and
then you start trying to build things
you start trying to build
larger code bases you start trying to
build things that have interfaces that
evolve
and that you give out to other people
and it turns out that
having the checked exception there
becomes an annoyance because the
compiler will not
let you not handle a checked except if
it sees you're calling a method with a
checked exception
it will say well either you need to
catch that in this method or you need to
publish
republish that exception in your own
signature
which unfortunately has led to a lot of
code where people just simply
catch and kill it's just oh this is so
annoying turning the compiler off
or they just catch the exception wrap it
in a runtime exception which
as it were is stealth and bubble it up
anyway
and the point here is that in large code
bases it has turned out
and this is an important thing this is a
feature of the java language it has
nothing to do with the jvm the jvm is
utterly oblivious to this kind of stuff
other jvm languages don't use it the
experiment was an interesting one and
actually i'd cite
a c-sharp rationale c-sharp doesn't have
them because of the java experience
it's kind of like yeah we saw what
happened there didn't work out you know
we understand that
it's not like the type signature i think
the way that i tend to put it uh
is um tolstoy's uh anna caronina
all happy families are the same but each
unhappy family is unhappy in its own way
it turns out that the ways in which you
might want to classify
failure are quite variable and change
over time even though the happy day
scenario might remain stable
you might and we suddenly discover
there's also a loss of encapsulation to
refer back to
our opening consideration is like you
start perhaps unintentionally
but in a larger codebase with lots of
developers it evolves that way you start
publishing details that are actually
quite private oh you're throwing that
kind of exception are you okay so it
becomes a real grind and it starts
adding to the boilerplate that trisha
was talking about you end up with
a lot of stuff either you're killing
these exceptions or you're having to
republish them and
every time something changes your
interface suddenly become unstable even
though its intention has remained stable
so it's one of those things great in
theory but not great in practice and
that became it's that idea also when you
start doing plug-in architectures
there's a lot of issues there and having
code execute
through things again do i need whose
exceptions do i need to publish
you know it starts becoming an
unnecessary set of negotiations for code
that would otherwise work
and and landers also kind of came along
well a bit later but nonetheless it's
that case of like well the lambda syntax
is intentionally light it takes a very
different philosophy
and so there's this idea that in many
projects anyway there is this idea of
like yet we don't use
checked exceptions anymore because
they're a bit of a burden we only use
the ones that
exist in the platforms that we're using
but don't make your own
is basically the advice but the reason
that advice is there is because still
we find people are taken with this
attractive idea
this idea that in theory this is a good
idea and advocating it's just like okay
um so my piece is called uncheck your
exceptions it's just like yep
it is a nice idea in theory and nobody's
doing anything
because they they mean to cause problems
for api evolution
but actually in practice we've learned
that and you know every language that's
been around for more than a few minutes
has picked up something that it's
probably regrets
you know it's like families you know
it's just there's something there
there's a sense of regret like yeah okay
that was a nice idea didn't work out but
we got other ideas that did
so your advice in short is just don't
use checks exceptions if you can
avoid it yeah you're creating your own
don't go down the path of creating
hierarchies of checked exceptions
because we end up trivializing what you
end up with is
people create code they say oh well you
know it's such a burden tell you what
we're going to have my library exception
and all of the things we'll
basically inherit from that and then you
end up losing the original intention
which was to be specific
you just say yeah we're just going to
throw the root exception
and we're going to put that in the
signature it's like well we've actually
lost that utility
of it throws an overflow it throws an
underflow and that's it
it's now it throws something from a
library and it's tended towards the top
and in the worst cases you'll just see
people go throws exception there we go
that should cover all sins
there's one more chapter that i found
specifically interesting and that is
chapter 81 about
co-routines co-routines are described as
lightweight alternatives to
threats in java but i think many people
might not be aware of what co-routines
are so let's start with that what are
co-routines and what is an example of a
situation in which a co-routine could be
useful
one of the things i liked about this
chapter is it actually explained
co-routines to me for
the first time and i was like oh now i
get co-routines
so i definitely want to recommend people
actually read that chapter in the book
because and specifically co-routines in
kotlin and
so it's a jvm language something kevin
and i wanted to put in the book was not
just
java the language things that java
developers needed to know but things
from other jvm languages
especially because some of those
features may find their way into java
the language in the future
but i think a lot of java programmers
like me are like i don't really know
what co-routines are or why they're
useful
yeah i think i think the thing about the
coaches is really nice together because
we were hoping for this language
diversity but then to get something very
specifically on co-routines
is nice because the coaching is kind of
making a bit of a comeback and it's one
of those things of
i think a number of languages in the
last decade have kind of added them in
kotlin being um
kind of a poster child for this uh
python formally acknowledged that it had
them it had them all along
in one sense generators and things like
that but properly formally acknowledged
they had them
and we're seeing these kind of features
creeping in to languages and
what i love about this is that coatings
are really old and they were just
fading when i entered the workforce and
i say this as a young man in his early
30s of course
when i was editing the workforce they
were just kind of going out
and we were at the point where process
creation was becoming cheaper people
were talking about processes
we were also moving to event driven
architectures and then
we were on the cusp of threading and
then threading became a big deal and you
know there was that and that kind of
look
it was the question of like how do i
express the idea that i wish to have
concurrent activation of things not
necessarily
you know we're talking pre-multi-core
not necessarily
actual true parallelism but at least
concurrent activation i don't want to
have to keep
starting up and shutting down state
machines to remember a thing that i
already had
and co routines used to be part of that
answer and they're a very old mechanism
melvin conway who is uh saint conway as
in conway's law
and conway's law was identified in 1968
melvin conway invented the co-routine in
so not a new idea at all but they used
to be the only way to really express
this kind of idea they used to be part
of the object paradigm
so similar 67 one of its big deals was
well objects exist in the world
concurrently with one another you don't
leave an object and it loses its memory
in its state you can go back to it so
similar had co-rooted so it's there all
along but
we've had so many other mechanisms that
have come into languages that we kind of
displace this but what's nice about
co-routines is they are
simple you don't get race conditions you
don't have all of that
i need to remember to synchronize this i
need to remember to lock this and unlock
that
you can't have a race condition with a
co routine it just simply says
i guess you were after an example a very
simple example is just simply that idea
of
okay you're alexa you're a lecturer i'm
a parser you break down some tokens and
i'll figure out where they fit
and it turns out that just give me the
next word is a classic example just give
me the next token
give me the next token i don't know what
state you're keeping about that you
don't need to be a full-blown object
you're just running a loop but the fact
is that loops shouldn't have to be
spread across multiple methods
it's a loop i'm going to return you
something we don't want to lose the loop
state
so people choreograph all kinds of
difficult code around this
and in fact i think most of the kind of
sax code that was written in the late
90s could be eliminated with
with co routines simply because it's a
case of like
i just want the next thing that's it
you've got state about how to manage it
and i'm going to continue this and i'm
asking you one question at a time
there's no simultaneity there's no
parallelism here
but we're both like we are partners that
one is not sub to the other subroutine
we are co with one another we're both
active and we're just exchanging we're
just having a conversation
taking turns and that seems an
incredibly reasonable thing to have in a
programming language
but culture and history kind of nudged
it out the way but we're kind of
realizing that
many of our concurrency problems are
actually a lot
well we're creating them rather than
solving them and just co-routines are a
very simple way of doing that and when
we lock them into the
those other tasks that people say well
this is why i was threading
it's normally something like
asynchronous io or timers and things
like that
and once you recognize it's actually
many of these things come down to a
really simple class of
problems as well right why don't we just
write a co-routine for that or
hide that away and then suddenly life
becomes a lot more single threaded
which is a lot easier for us mere
mortals to reason about
okay those were all the chapters that i
wanted to cover but i was also really
curious about
the process of writing the book because
we've alluded to this already a little
bit
there are many chapters written by other
people and then you wrote a few chapters
also
and then you edited the book with the
two of you
so how did you deal with different
chapters
giving conflicting advice were there
chapters that were like
mutually exclusive like oh we have to
pick either this one
or that one how did you manage different
opinions and
because the book does feel like a hole
that is somewhat consistent i'm really
curious how you did that
we actually wanted conflicting opinions
in various places where we didn't
disagree with the opinions i think
so for example like kevin just talked
about checked exceptions we were kind of
interested in maybe a piece which was
like
the you know stating why checked
obsessions is
would be a good thing when there'll be a
good use case with
certifications my colleague mala wrote a
piece about why certifications are very
valuable
and i went out and sought a counterpiece
to that because i know a number of my
friends and ex-colleagues are much
more anti-certifications
interestingly by having those different
points of view you can actually come to
they don't necessarily contradict each
other so for example the certification
one
was like you know that the computer
science answer for everything is it
depends
so the certifications one was if you
need to do this
certifications might be a way to forge
that path
on the other hand if you're looking for
a particular type of person
a certification is not going to take
these types of boxes
so it's quite good to get what looks
like on the surface conflicting advice
because it actually helps you weigh up
you know sometimes it's this and
sometimes it's that yeah and that was
something that
we were both very keen on this idea that
yeah although we have our own
particular perspectives as trisha said
when there's something that's
genuinely wrong yeah we're not going to
do that it's a case of like should i
sell my grandmother well no
no we're not gonna have a counterpiece
to you shouldn't uh we
you should that doesn't make sense and
if you're gonna have an argument with
the compiler you're gonna lose you know
in other words anything that's
intentionally wrong so there is a kind
of right and wrong here but
there are so many things that are it
depends
and in those cases just giving people
giving the reader this is not a book by
one person
this is a book by many people and so
therefore we're trying to show you
sample the landscape and sample the
views that are out there in 97 things
you know it's not a perfect sample
but we'd like to give you that
representation and that's quite
important because
otherwise it makes it sound like there
is a foregone conclusion that there is a
right answer in a case where actually
maybe there's a bit more discussion to
be had
and regardless of our own opinions on
some things we recognize well that's my
kind of opinion here
but you know what there are decent
people who don't believe that or have
some points to make against that so we
want their voices as well
so if this were a single book with a
single storyline that had to be coherent
that would be a very different kind of
thing but we actually have an
opportunity here
to say hey look here's the range of
thinking you the reader
get to figure it out for yourself and
that i think is quite important because
in those cases where there isn't a fixed
answer
you've got to show that the landscape's
a bit bigger
as trisha was pointing out that these
things are often complementary they
sometimes
appear initially contradictory and you
can see a few things where they don't
agree but then you suddenly
actually there's more to this than meets
the eye and it's that
you know it's that multiple points of
view that becomes valuable
yeah and it is often of course this it
depends what might be very good advice
for one situation just doesn't really
fit
a totally different company or a
different type of programming language
and again that kind of informs why we
were really keen on getting
some representation of other jvm
languages otherwise it does look like
that
you know it's only java well no it isn't
there's a lot of other things going on
there so
i think that's quite important and
that's something you can do more easily
with more people which is the structure
of the book as an editor it's kind of
challenging when you found pieces that
you disagreed with because you were like
okay i don't necessarily agree with this
but is it that i don't agree with it
because it's wrong or is it i don't
agree with it because it's against my
opinion
and it was as an editor it's really
eye-opening to have those sort of
internal conversations of like
oh i'm gonna have to open my eyes to
other points of view here
yeah i think that's and so it's kind of
interesting when we were going through
because we received all of these pieces
some of which
people contacted us with some of which
we went out and sought
and we had there's a whole lot of
articles up on medium
that were kind of published through that
initially it was kind of like a
trial space but also people were able to
submit through a form
and uh google docs so we're getting all
these things in different sources
different people
and obviously we get more than 97 things
so we have to there has to be a decision
process so we had
to you know kind of from the beginning
based on my
previous experience because i edited 97
things every programmer should know
one of the things that i found was
useful is make sure that we
limit the number of contributions from
an individual
because otherwise there can be too much
no matter how brilliant their pieces are
that's the problem sometimes that's the
most frustrating thing is like somebody
gives you all of these wonderful ones we
have that
more than once people giving us loads of
great stuff
but actually the whole thing is to give
voice so limit of three that was our
kind of like that was our cutoff
but that also boosts the number of
people that ultimately get represented
in the book that's what you end up with
when you um sort of cap it
but it does mean that you're kind of
looking sometimes you've got two pieces
of advice that do say the same
thing and you kind of you're looking for
a reason to
you know decide between one and the
other and so trisha and i had a number
of conversations some of the you know
different categories yep this one's easy
this one's in this one
is easy we're not going to include this
one and then we have this kind of gray
territory this
in between kind of like oh i like it but
or we've already got too many pieces
from this person and and so on and those
were the ones that attracted discussion
so which i wouldn't i would never
sacrifice that because i think that's
part of the joy of this and you end up
learning more about it and we're each
making the case
on the whole we were pretty much on the
same page i don't really think we had
any kind of like
anything that was contradictory we just
sometimes would want to cast a vote for
one rather than another but we ended up
with fairly you know fairly much in the
same space
and honestly i'm going to say it was
actually easier choosing these 97
with tricia than when i was the sole
editor of 97 things every programmer
should know
i honestly i probably disagree with
myself a lot more so it was kind of
interesting
just that process but you're getting
somebody else's point of view and
it creates a balanced hole and trisha
and i come from very different points of
view when it comes to this so that
i think helps the roundedness of the
book and the kind of what gets included
what gets represented and who
is in there yeah that makes sense
because as i said from the reader's
perspective
it does feel like a consistent group of
tips or things
and even though sometimes within a
chapter different viewpoints are being
presented as a whole it feels really
as a consistent story are there any of
your favorite chapters that i might have
missed so we've covered the ones that i
thought were most interesting but maybe
you also want to say well if you are
reading the book then you should
definitely shouldn't miss
chapter the editor card that i've played
for years which is i don't pick
favorites
and i wait for people to specifically
raise one
you know that's first of all mine
because otherwise i know that what
normally happens
is either it's the thing that most
recently occurred to me it's like that
thing when somebody asks you know what's
your favorite film or what's your
favorite
sometimes you think you have a favorite
but sometimes it's just the thing you
thought about most recently and so you
you end up with a recency bias which i'm
not going to play favorites i can let
trisha do that she wants but i'm not
going to play favorites with this one
yeah no i am going to make a
recommendation you see there's 97 things
1 through 97. honestly read them all
that is cheating what about you trisha
do you have any favorites well apart
from i guess your own chapter
so that's the easy answer as well mine
are obviously my favorites i actually
i'm a bit more general than that i
one of the things i really liked so i
joined halfway through the project i
didn't start off the project i joined to
edit a bit later on
and one of the things i quite liked with
what we had when i joined and the pieces
which came a bit later on as well is
that we had a lot of stuff on automated
testing
and that the value of automated testing
good ways of doing automated testing and
i'm a big fan of that because i kind of
discovered automated testing
a little bit later on in my career early
in my career i saw junit testing and i
was like i don't really get it because
our tests were always failing
and so once i worked for somewhere where
automated testing was like
it really worked and it really gave you
the confidence to do your refactoring it
gave you the confidence to do these
small commits that i was talking about
later
then i'm just passionate about anyone
who can talk about why automated testing
is a good thing
great then that concludes the episode
for today
where can we read more about this book
of course we have some links i think
that we can put in the show notes the
link to the book
other places where we can read something
about there is a twitter stream
at 97 underscore things if i
remember the use of the joy of
underscore
97 things for some reason had originally
disappeared and
yes it is 97 underscore things so if
there's any kind of announcements really
there are other books in the 97 things
series but we kind of uh it has a slight
bias
to the java stuff at the moment this the
stream
there's also the medium blogs 97 dash
things you can dig around that and find
kind of early drafts of many of the
things that became chapters
and i think honestly if you just google
the 97 things is such a distinct number
or such a distinct phrase you'll find
some of the other books in the series
but if you put 97 things java then it
narrows it down really quite quickly
yeah and we also make sure that we put a
link of course to the twitter
to the medium blog and to the book
directly in the show note so it's easy
for people to check it out
yeah and you can find the every now and
then there's kind of little discussions
that pop up trisha and i did a coverage
thing last year where
it was kind of the book of the week and
you know focused on that people ask
questions
uh we responded and so on so so yeah
there's a there's a few things
around and about and some very uh very
nice reviews
that are not amazon or o'reilly based
around so yeah there's
you know the good stuff's out there well
great thanks both of you so much for
being on the show today
thank you thanks very much this is
felina for software engineering radio
[Music]
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening